<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Answer to the letter written to a member of Parliament upon the occasion of some votes of the House of Commons against their late speaker and others</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3417</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R110</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13060692</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13060692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97022</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97022)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 406:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Answer to the letter written to a member of Parliament upon the occasion of some votes of the House of Commons against their late speaker and others</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52 [i.e. 54] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANSWER TO THE LETTER Written to a <hi rend="blackletterType">Member</hi> of <hi rend="blackletterType">Parliament,</hi> Upon the Occaſion of ſome VOTES OF THE HOUSE of COMMONS againſt their late Speaker, and Others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCXCV.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97022:3"/>
            <head>THE ANSWER, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen you did me the Honour to write me a Letter upon the occaſion of ſome Votes paſſed in our Houſe againſt the late Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and others, I had then leave given me to retire into the Country for my Health: It was the Reaſon I could return you Thanks no ſooner, for the Favour you put upon me to read your Thoughts upon the Affair handled by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons againſt ſuch Members as had taken Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for expediting of Buſineſs. I do, Sir, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally run into all the Meaſures of good and unbiaſſed Men, for the Honour, Safety, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of my Country; which never more wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted good Example and Support than at this Day. I muſt likewiſe tell you, That I ever lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Freedom and Ingenuity, and will not ſtick
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97022:4"/>to give your Letter ſuch a ſuitable Return as may be conſiſtent with your own and its Character. I confeſs, when I read your two firſt Periods, I had ſome Difficulties to gueſs who might be the Author; but after I had proceeded mid-way in your hiſtorical and political Reflexions, it was no great trouble to find you out. So equal a Pace you tread in your admired way of writing, that it made me call to mind a frugal Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, once my Neighbour in the Country, who had the Art to fit a Servant of his own to ſo many Uſes, that upon occaſion you found the ſame Man a Gardener, Cook, Coach-man, and Barber, by turns. I muſt ſay, That in your learned Works now abroad in the World you uſe the ſame Repetitions in your <hi>Obſervators, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dications, Inquiries, Anſwers to Declarations, Great Baſtards Protectors to little ones,</hi> and in your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to your Friends: For had not the Letter you did me the Honour to write me exceeded the Bonds of your Ordinary <hi>Obſervators,</hi> I had taken it for granted you had began a freſh to your Politicks. I find you ſuſtain ſudden and ill diſgeſted Thoughts, with ſo many <hi>Greek, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Tranſcripts, abundance whereof, according to your Cuſtom, are but upon Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and ſtoln from ſome Gentlemens Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97022:4"/>where you are ſaid to intrude with a great deal of Impudence and ill Breeding.</p>
            <p>You begin then, Sir, your firſt Flight with the amends the Parliament has made, in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearch of the Blood-ſuckers of the Nation, for the Loſs of an incomparable Queen; but that I may endeavor the better Anſwer, you will give me leave to inform you a little in our Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to which by Birth and Knowledge you may be a Stranger.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of Commons in <hi>England</hi> contains the Repreſentatives of the People, originally cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to that Honour by the King's Reſcript; they meet where it pleaſeth his Majeſty to appoint them, and are generally called either to give Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the preſſing Affairs of the Kingdom in War and Peace, or to give their Conſent to the Eſtabliſhment of wholeſom Laws, or to humbly repreſent the Neceſſities of the People, and their Grievances, that thereby redreſs may be had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and according to Law. You know the Houſe of Commons is no Judicatory, nor cannot do ſo much as can any ordinary Juſtice of Peace, Adminiſter an Oath.</p>
            <p>The Houſe of Lords, Spiritual and Temporal, make up the other two Eſtates, and are a Court of Judicatory, when aſſembled together by the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97022:5"/>King's Order; they can determine finally in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Differences between Man and Man. And if Bribery ſhould unhappily get footing in that Houſe, the uſual Puniſhment thereof ought na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally to follow: But, at the ſame time, what is unhandſomly taken without the knowledge of a Peer by any of his Family, be it Wife, Son, Daughter, or Servant, it cannot be charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelf as a Fault, if he have no acceſſion to the Thing.</p>
            <p>I ſhould be heartily glad, and I think it would contribute both for the Honour and God of the Nation, That there might be an eſtabliſhed and explained Law againſt all taking of Money in both Houſes; to compaſs which, I think, it would be fit to go to the moſt neceſſary ways to reform a Houſe of Commons. There be two radical Evils that ought to be remedied; the one is, The manner of Elections, where, beſides all the uſual Diſorders and Debauche to exceſs, there Reigns a popular Partiality for the Richeſt or Profuſeſt to run away with the Election up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any occaſion; and Vertue, which is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally modeſt, to be neglected: But the greater is, Many Men of uneaſy Circumſtances do get into being Parliament-men, and keep there, as in a Sanctuary, to ſecure their Eſtates and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97022:5"/>from juſt Debts: From which laſt Source (intolerable in a well-governed Nation) there is given a natural and neceſſary handle to take and retain what in Conſcience ought to be paid; innumerable Families ſuffering by an abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Conſtitution, ſo much famed, as being the Nations great Barricade againſt the Enemies of Liberty and Property, the darling of Mankind; and without which they muſt be uneaſie and unhappy.</p>
            <p>What our Houſe has done in confining or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling two of its Members, to vindicate the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of its illuſtrious Body, does not want Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and Obloquy from the moſt ſenſible part of the Nation, and Strangers, who know not to this day upon what Law the diſpleaſure was founded. You ſeem ſatisfied to rally the Misfortune of two Gentlemen; and while you endavor to deſcend your Malice to Poſterity, they have ſtill a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſtock of Vertue to defend them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's true,</hi> you ſay, <hi>it will look but with an ill Grace beyond Sea, to hear of one of the Engliſh Parliaments ſent to the Tower for Bribery; ſo great a Name for the moſt incorrupted Body of Men in all Chriſtendom has the Houſe of Commons of</hi> England <hi>ver born.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:97022:6"/>
            <p>Believe me, Sir, as you do not ſeem Learned at home, ſo give me leave to conclude you Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the abroad World; Strangers under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſo little of our Conſtitution, that hardly any Foreigner has writ tolerable of the Forms or Power of our Houſe; and to believe us an incorrupted Body, what greater Arguments can be taken againſt that than from your own Mouth? Who often have been heard to aver, That in former Reigns many Members of the Houſe of Commons were Penſioners to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and the <hi>French</hi> King; and that certain Sums of Money, ſo appointed, had been put at the Roots of Trees in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Park, and other hidden Corners, where after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Parliament-men went or ſent to fetch them: But the Misfortune was, there was no ſearch made into the Matter then.</p>
            <p>Sir, I cannot enough admire why you are ſo hard upon Mr. G. It may be he has not paid you the Deference and Reſpect you expected of him; or has he incurred your Diſpleaſure, as did unhappily once the Maſter of a Tavern, for neglecting to give you the firſt and loweſt Bow; or, according to the manner of ſome other Gentlemen, who have taken upon the right Altitude of your Parts, has ſlighted your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97022:6"/>and Perſon. There may be ſome Reaſon why you hate Sir <hi>J.T.</hi> he it was who gave you a ſoft Reprimand for an Indiſcretion or Miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor committed by you againſt the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>England,</hi> in your authentique Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, called the <hi>new Obſervator;</hi> where you ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed quite of another Mind than you are at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. Here it is you cannot endure one Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Money deſigned for the Publick be put to any other Uſe; there you can diſpenſe with a Million at a time, rather to be thrown in the Sea, than that the Houſe ſhould proſecute or find out who did purloin it.</p>
            <p>In this ext Period you enter fairly upon your large and well-accommodating Field of <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtories and Examples: Here it is you bring in the unparalleled <hi>Antoninus,</hi> and his happy Reign, with a Prayer of your own, there may be no Ground for comparing the preſent <hi>England</hi> to the then depraved <hi>Rome.</hi> For my own part I go ſo far along with you, That I think we exceed <hi>Rome</hi> in all that's Corrupt, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, and Confuſed; without even holding that ſmall remainder of Vertue that ſtuck ſtill to ſome of the <hi>Romans</hi> in the worſt of Times.</p>
            <p>The World is convinced how great a Maſter the King is of all heroick Vertue; and methinks
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97022:7"/>you might have allowed him rather a Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to <hi>Julius Ceſar</hi> than to <hi>Marcus Antoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus:</hi> For they both deſcended from noble An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors; they had both grea Enemies in their Youth, and firſt Age. <hi>Ceſar</hi> had <hi>Sylla,</hi> and his Faction; King <hi>William</hi> had <hi>de Witt,</hi> and his: They both came into <hi>Britain</hi> with a foreign Force. <hi>Ceſar</hi> came to remove Barbarity and to eſtabliſh the <hi>Roman</hi> Law and Civility; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty came to vindicate and aſſert the Laws eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; they both ſucceeded in their Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; they both entered the Iſland with a great Fleet; they both met with Misfortunes in their Fleets; they both returned to the Continent, having compoſed their Inſulary Affairs; they both returned to make War againſt <hi>France. Ceſar</hi> conquered and reduced it into the Form of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince in the ſpace of Ten years; his Majeſty is now pretty well advanced in the Seventh years War: And, I hope, by it hath continued Ten years, or it may be ſhorter time, <hi>France</hi> ſhall be brought to be as eaſie to <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>Ceſar</hi> made it to <hi>Rome.</hi> Both Generals were almoſt Forty years old when they began the career of their Fortunes; both Generals were born in a popular State, that had their Denomination from the Number Seven; <hi>Rome</hi> was built upon Seven Hills, and the united
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97022:7"/>States are made up of Seven Provinces. <hi>Ceſar</hi> was Conſul, and Captain-General of the <hi>Roman</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; King <hi>William</hi> is Stadtholder and Captain-General of the States their Fleet, and Forces. Here, Sir, is much more Ground for a Parallel, than that of your cold-headed Philoſopher <hi>Antoninus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are ſome Vices the illuſtrious Crimes of the antient</hi> Romans, <hi>ſuch as Emulation, Ambition, and Thirſt after Dominion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, As I cannot allow Emulation in Vertue a a Crime, ſo I find you ignorant of the <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquity, when you bing in Ambition and Thirſt afer Dominion to have raiſed their firſt Empire. It was Valour, Parſimony, and great Honeſty and Simplicity in their Manners and Actions, and an abſolute Neceſſity of defending themſelves, being Strangers, and <hi>Rome,</hi> from falling under the Power of her Neighbors. You give an Inſtance of Ignorance, when you call <hi>Rome</hi> a beggarly Village; that City, though it begun ſmall, was never a Village. You ought to know the Occaſion why <hi>Romulus</hi> killed his Brother <hi>Remus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next Place you aſcend for ſome Pages your Chariot of Triumph with the antient <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> as <hi>Cincinnatus, Attilus Regulus,</hi> and <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Aemilius:</hi> Here it is you have an infinite ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97022:8"/>and immortal Scope for your Pen; on theſe Pinacles it is you hang out your Ornaments, that ſerve you alike for all Holydays; out of theſe your Magazines do you take upon all Occaſions <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Weapons to ruin Yours, and the Enemies of the State, as you call them; for the which great and generous Undertaking you deſerve at leaſt a Statue for your ſelf. Thus, Sir, after a long and tedious Journey through Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and ancient Examples, you arrive in your noted and well-frequented Port, of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s All being at Stake, Liberty, Religion, Laws, and Property; and not only ſo, but the Fate of Chriſtendom. And, in one Word, here your Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is employed in running through the whole popular Strain, in how far every one is engaged for the gneeral Weal of the Nation, that Corruption may be diſcouraged, and the publick Money employed according to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Givers; in all which <hi>England</hi> is beholden to you: Yet I muſt tell you, by the way, there was upon a time a very bad Man gave good Council in a popular State, and when it came to be debated whether it ſhould be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or not, it was allowed by all to be good Council; but that it would be ill receive by the People, becauſe of the lame and narrow Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97022:8"/>of the Perſon who gave it, he being a very ill Man.</p>
            <p>You ſeem to exert your Malice, and merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Pen, at a time in that the whole Subject of your Pamphlet is only levelled at two or three Perſons whoſe Vertue, Capacity, and Service to their Country, upon many Occaſions, cannot be overthrown or defaced by your Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>I thought the ſevere Checks you have ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſo juſtly met withal, might have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with you to keep to your promiſe, to drop your Pen for good and all, being you were made ſufficiently to underſtand your Incapacity and Inability to manage it: But there may be ſome Reaſons have induced you to keep it ſtill employ'd, as the renewing your proſtrate and proſtitute Flatteries to your Friends and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors; or perhaps after almoſt Three years ſilence, you will let the World know your late Improvement in ancient Hiſtory, to which you were a Stranger.</p>
            <p>But being we are about the matter of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, there is, Sir, among many, one kind of Corruption lies particularly heavy upon your Vertue; and that is, the horrible Flatteries that are ſquander'd over all your Scriblings. I am
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97022:9"/>confident that Antiquity never ſaw ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Perſons ſet off with Praiſes due to Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, as have been ſince the laſt reflouriſhing of Letters in <hi>Europe;</hi> Vertue and Vice, Truth and Falſhood, Juſtice and Injuſtice, are ſo ill diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by mercenary Pens, That many good Men do almoſt wiſh the World had remained, as to ſome part, in <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Ignorance to this day.</p>
            <p>It is a great Truth, <hi>That</hi> England <hi>has much, and it may be more than is neceſſary at Stake.</hi> The auguſt Houſe of Commons had framed, near the cloſe of the laſt Seſſions, ſuch Reſolutions as were truly fitted to the Intereſt and Honour of their Country; and I wiſh their next Meeting may perfect what was then happily begun, and then ſufficient and well-grounded Matter will be given you to eternize that incorrupted and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Body, by your well-faſhion'd Pen, if you like the Subject better than that of Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>You ask leave to do the <hi>Romans, Greeks;</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians</hi> Juſtice, aſſuring the World they embezled no publick Money, but kept it equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacred with what they conſecrated to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their Gods. For the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee any great Reaſon you have to undertake
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97022:9"/>their Defence, being their Hiſtory and Learning is loſt, ſave what we have, in ſo far as they had to do with the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans</hi> in War or Treaty: But I am led to believe, That they were not a better ſort of People than the States of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Greece;</hi> but that almoſt every Age among theſe two Nations had its Corruptions and Embezlements of publick and ſacred Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, I am perſwaded. To omit many among the <hi>Greeks,</hi> Do you remember what council <hi>Alciabiades</hi> gave to his Uncle <hi>Pericles,</hi> when he found him much taken up what way to render an Account to <hi>Athens</hi> for her publick Money? Did he not deſire him rather to find out a way to make no accompt with them of that City at all? Do not you find that <hi>Pericles</hi> not only uſed the publick Money of <hi>Athens</hi> as he thought fit, but laid likewiſe hand upon the ſacred Money repoſited in that City by, for its better Security againſt barbarous hands? But his good Fortune, his Character, and the pliable Age he lived in, ſecured him. Do you remember why <hi>Ariſtides</hi> and <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> were baniſhed. <hi>Scipio African</hi> the Elder was not free from the ſame Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But his Brother, the <hi>Aſiatique Scipio,</hi> was highly Guilty. For the <hi>Romans</hi> robbing the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Gods, there is nothing more infamous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97022:10"/>than <hi>Sylla</hi>'s robbing the Confederate Temple at <hi>Delphi; Craſſus</hi> robbed that of <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> that of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſay, and ſo do I, <hi>That upon Exigencies it's no Sacrilege to borrow from the Churches even their moſt ſacred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils; but you thank Heaven that we are under no ſuch Hardſhip in this War.</hi> Fro my part I am glad that our Churches are reduced to the modeſt and primitive Form of Worſhip, and that our Altars have no ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Ornaments to ſpare; but you ought to be perſwaded of the Zeal of the Church for the publick Good, when having no ſtore of treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Money, nor Ornaments, ſhe runs willingly into the Meaſures of giving chearfully every Year a Fifth part of her whole; which as it is but Duty, is ſtill more in proportion than the <hi>Gallican</hi> Clergy grant, even his Year, to the <hi>French</hi> King, though they ſhould continue ſo to the end of the War.</p>
            <p>But that Mankind may be beholden to your illuſtrious Wit, and rare Genie, you are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to deſcend from your <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Flights, and give us a Period or two purely your own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You are plagued, you ſay, by your Neighbors in the Country with a thouſand Queſtions about</hi> Mr. <hi>G.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97022:10"/>Sometimes they ask what great Things the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman hath done for his Country, to deſerve ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable a Place? They expect you ſhould acquaint sthem with the Oppoſition he made to the violent Courſes of the laſt Reigns; or of ſome Loſs he ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained by them. They enquire about his Behavior in the laſt Revolution, and what wonderful At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievoments he has done to ſupport the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. All which Queſtions, you being a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Gentleman, deſire me to anſwer, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as you ſay, I may know him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though, Sir, I may be as much a Stranger to him as your ſelf, yet you having reduced a thouſand Queſtions to two or three, I have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Pains in the Thing, and learned from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Mouths, That Mr. <hi>G.</hi> is a Gentleman of very good Parts, and of a plentiful Eſtate, which you know ſounds very well here in <hi>England:</hi> That he had Merit enough to bring him to ſo profitable a Place, if his good Fortune had been equal to have maintained him in it: That he made the ſame Oppoſitions to the violent Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the laſt Reigns many other honeſt Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men had done, who durſt only regret what was not in their Power to help. As for his Beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior in the late Revolution, he fillowed the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures taken by all the ſound and good part of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97022:11"/>the Nation; he took the Oaths chearfully to his Majeſty, and was never accuſed for doing an unbecoming Thing to his Maſter.</p>
            <p>And, Sir, had you known any worſe Thing of him, I am bold to think you would not have given me the trouble of your Queſtions.</p>
            <p>You are pleaſed to continue and bring in a witty Jeſt of your own; <hi>Where Mr,</hi> G. <hi>and Sir</hi> J. T. <hi>being the Subject matter of your Diſcourſe, as ſeldom they fail to be; a Neighbor of your own, but no great Politician, you ſay, (if Honeſty be the beſt Policy your Neighbor may be ſuch a Politician as your ſelf) to extenuate Mr.</hi> G. <hi>Fault was of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, That the neceſſity of his Circumſtances in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a numerous Family, or Daughters to Portion, might tempt him to take</hi> 200 <hi>Gnineas: And after a mighty Debate among your Country Stateſmen, it was reſolved by the Board, That nothing but the Circumſtance mentioned by your Neighbor could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the Bribery. But you hap'ning to come in at the end of this wiſe Debate, found that skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from one Thing to another the Company came at laſt to run down their Comrade, for imagining</hi> 200 <hi>Guineas a compotent Portion for a Daughter of Mr.</hi> G. <hi>But to bring off your Friend, though at the Expence of a piece of Hiſtory, you were forced to tell them, That even in the height of the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97022:11"/>
               <hi>Empire, ſuch a Sum would have been eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a conſiderable Portion for the greateſt and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt Senators of</hi> Rome <hi>to give with a Daughter: And that the Daughter of the Immortal</hi> Scipio Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricanus, (<hi>a Man not much inferior to Mr. G.</hi>) <hi>was ſaid to have had a great Portion given her by the Senate (for her Father had nothing to give her) though Maſter of the Spoils of</hi> Carthage, <hi>when it amounted but to</hi> 2000 <hi>Pieces of Braſs-money, which comes far ſhort of</hi> 200 <hi>Guineas of ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have almoſt tranſcribed your Jeſt, being very well ſatisfied that it is purely your own: And I dare ſay you may freely enjoy it, without any one's diſputing you the Honour to have been its Author. For after a dull and inſipid Narration of you know not what, nor to what purpoſe, you are obliged to run back again to your <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory to ſupport you; ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Pieces of ill told Hiſtory may go down with your good-natured Friends in the Country, but they will not ſo in the City: For to ſay the Truth, you do not underſtand what you pretend to. Pray, Sir, who taught you that the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was at the height in <hi>Scipio</hi>'s Days? Did not he conclude a Piece, though up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hard Terms, for the <hi>Charthaginians?</hi> Was not all <hi>France, Spain, Germany, Britain, Suiſſe, Illyricum,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97022:12"/>Dalmatia, Panonia,</hi> all higher <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> then unſubdued? Which Provinces make almoſt Three parts of Four of all the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. You do not ſeem to underſtand the <hi>Roman</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney better than their Hiſtory; for the 2000 Pieces of Braſs given by the Senate to your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal <hi>Scipio,</hi> the <hi>African</hi>'s Daughter, they may ariſe to more than Four hundred Guineas; if you will conſider that the <hi>Romans</hi> had Braſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money from the Value of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Two-pence to a Noble: And it's like the Senate would not beſtow it of the loweſt Coin to the Daughter of ſo great a Father. Beſides, Money was then of many times a higher Value than at preſent; and the Senate thought it a fit Portion for the Lady, whoſe Vertue according to her Sex did well deſerve it, ſeeing it was nothing inferior to that of her Father. It would appear by you that there was a mortal and an immortal <hi>Scipio</hi> the <hi>African,</hi> for there was two of the Name; but that by a happineſs peculiar to your ſelf, you beſtow the Actions of the one upon the other: For it was the mortal <hi>Scipio</hi> that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <hi>Carthage,</hi> and who made himſelf Maſter of her Spoils; the immortal <hi>Scipio</hi> was only Maſter of the Spoils of <hi>Hannibal</hi>'s Army, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Battle of <hi>Zama.</hi> But why the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97022:12"/>
               <hi>Scipio?</hi> Have you not condemned that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet to be given to great Men in your other Libels? You ought upon occaſion to allow your Friends the ſame Liberties you take, or give Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why they ſhould not uſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But you leave, you ſay, this ridiculous Digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> Ridiculous enough in Conſcience, and you had done much better not to have made it.</p>
            <p>After which, the excellent and nice Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you make upon the proceedure of the Houſe of Commons, in expelling their late Speaker, is worthy their publick Thanks; you have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed your Pen no where more handſomly than by raiſing a juſt Admiration of the Candor, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bity, Incorruption, Sedfaſtneſs, and Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Houſe in the Thing; you ſay, nothing <hi>can gain them a greater Reputation abroad.</hi> Though Sir, as I have already mentioned, Strangers are ignorant of our Conſtitutions, they are pretty well acquainted with our Manners and Charac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter here in <hi>England:</hi> And the Nations abroad are generally verſed in the Civil Law, and know what is to be ſaid upon the Matter as well as we; for I preſume there is no municipal Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom that has defined the <hi>Fault charged</hi> upon the Speaker to be a Bribery: For <hi>future Ages</hi> it is hard to determine, but the Age we live in all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97022:13"/>the World over is nice in every Thing, (ſave Vertue) and it is good to be upon the ſtrong Side in Calumnies, and to charge the weakeſt to our beſt Advantage.</p>
            <p>Your next Flight is to the Rabinical and Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Learning; this is a new Thing, and juſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la-mode to your preſent Pamphlet. <hi>You ſay that none were admitted into that great Council who had the leaſt ſtain upon his Reputation of Honour, nor was they allowed to ask a juſt Debt of a Man during his Sute before them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pray, Sir, was it allowed them by the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Stations to refuſe the Payment of juſt Debts to ſuch as they owed them to? You give a Deſcription of the Room they met in, and of their Rites; but neither the one nor the other reſemble our Houſe, and we are not for Innovations, but you will continue your imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Digreſſions.</p>
            <p>I am glad to find, by your next Period, that the Houſe has hit ſo juſtly upon a middle way to pleaſe you in the manner of expelling their late Speaker: I ſhall make no further Queſtion but with the two or three expelled Members all Corruption is put out of Doors, and am over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed to think that Antiquity cannot produce an Example among the <hi>Amphictions, Areopagites,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97022:13"/>nor in the moſt incorrupt Times of the Senates of <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Athens;</hi> where ſo great an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, not bounded by any poſitive Law, ſhould purely from a Senſe of Vertue be equally Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to all Corruption in taking of Money.</p>
            <p>I cannot allow of the new Name you Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Houſe withal, in calling it <hi>an Engliſh Sanhedrim:</hi> For that neither the original Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the one, nor the fundamental Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the other, will bear it; nay, nor the Rabinical Deſcription you have juſt now given. Beſides, we <hi>Engliſh</hi> are fond of what's properly our own, and mortally hate Strangers; and it may be you may think, all Things conſidered, that we have juſt Reaſon to do ſo.</p>
            <p>Your Indignation continues at a ſtrange Rate againſt the Speaker; we know you owe him no Kindneſs, nor do you ſhew whole Affair, I find the Hardſhip, or rather juſt Mortification our Houſe put upon you, was almoſt neceſſary at that time for your Reputation; your <hi>Obſervators</hi> ſinking ſo much from day to day, That had not good Fortune ſent you before us, purely for your want of Senſe and Matter, in a Week or two more you muſt have dropt your Pen.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97022:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Poet had Reaſon to exclaim againſt the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Hunger of God in the Times he lived in; but had he lived in ours, he had much more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to do ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know, Sir, that the Poet you mention did exclaim as much againſt the ſacred Hunger of Gold in theſe as in thoſe Days: For his Poem has no Relation to the Time he lived in; upon the contrary, it has regard to a matter of Fact before the Foundation of <hi>Rome.</hi> And is this the unfortunate <hi>Priam,</hi> ſeeing all his Affairs go to ruin, and moſt of his Sons killed in defence of their Country, did ſend one of thoſe as yet alive to a neighbouring King and Confederate of <hi>Thrace,</hi> called <hi>Polymneſter?</hi> Who ſeeing the <hi>Trojan</hi> Affairs decline did, according to the Practice of many bad Men, make his Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a falling King and State; kill the poor <hi>Polidore,</hi> and poſſeſs himſelf of the great Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure had been ſent along with him. The Poets own Words do beſt expreſs the Thing.</p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hunc Polidorum auri quondam cum pondere magno,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Infelix Priamus furtim mandarat alendum</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Threïcio regi; cum jam diffideret armis</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dardaniis, cingique urbem obſidione videret.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ille ut opes fractae Teucrum &amp; Fortuna receſſit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fas omne abrumpit; Polidorum obtruncat &amp; auro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vi potitur, quid non Mortalia Pectora cogis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auri ſacra Fames!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97022:14"/>
            <p>I go readily along with your Reflexion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the State of the Nation. <hi>That ſhould unbiaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Strangers come amongſt us, and obſerve nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly our Condition, and the Actings of many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Land, they ſhould eaſily be led to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it upon point of Breaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be but too many important Truths for that Suppoſition, and ſmall Remedy provided againſt them.</p>
            <p>In this Paragraph your Stock fails you, and forces you back for a freſh Supply to your own Country; whence you bring an Impoſtor, and put him in the ſame Period and Example with <hi>Solomon,</hi> withou your having any regard to Senſe, or Coherence, in the matter you treat about.</p>
            <p>Then you come to a civil, good natured, and mannerly Queſtion; <hi>Whether theſe Men that take Money with both hands from their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men might not be tempted to the ſame from its Enemies?</hi> It is your own Opinion, <hi>You had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deal with a</hi> French <hi>than</hi> Engliſh <hi>Cuſtomer.</hi> (And who knows but you may do ſo?) There be, according to common Fame, as black Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles in the Legend of your Life, as is that; though bad enough: But you are in a Miſtake to think it more allowable to ſell Country
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97022:15"/>and Liberty, and all what ought to be moſt dear to us, to our greateſt Enemies, rather than to allow a preſent to be given at home betwixt Man and Man, in the neceſſary Commerce of Affairs, where no Law intervenes to define it to be a Fault. And I am aſtoniſhed to hear you ſpeak of the <hi>French</hi> King's having ſuperfluous Caſh; it is not long ſince you allowed that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hardly to have Bread, nor their King Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to entertain the War. It is an unhappy and unadviſed Expreſſion, after his Majeſty has given us Aſſurance, by his Royal Word, that a Stop has been put to the Progreſs of their Arms, to make new Nerves of War ſpring up to them afreſh. You continue to be uncharitable, and purſue your Revenge beyond the Boundary of Honour. You will not allow Gentlemen that have given repeated Inſtances of Fidelity, and and done upon occaſion great and good Service to the Government, to retain Sentiments of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Juſtice to their Country, even in their Hearts and Wiſhes; and would have the World believe with you, That the want of Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to better their Condition by Strangers, and by our and their Enemies, keeps them within the Limits of what they owe to and do for the Nation. Notwithſtanding the laſt Clamour and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97022:15"/>Noiſe raiſed by their Enemies upon the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure of the Houſe againſt them, it will not be eaſily in their Power to keep them under any Aſperſion during their Lives, or to render their Memory ungrateful to their Country or Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: And it has no Relation to their Character, <hi>That he who can be bought for Money will go for the higheſt Price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are extreamly ill informed in a long Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Intelligence you attribute to Monſieur <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> which may give the World to know that you underſtand neither ancient nor modern Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs aright: No <hi>Colbert</hi> had ever a hand in the Matter. But 'tis impoſſible your Stories ſhould want Authors, you are ſo well qualified to find them out upon all Occaſions.</p>
            <p>You bring in a Regret, <hi>But alas! my Friend, when the love of Money gets the aſcendant all other Paſſions and Intereſts muſt ſtoop to its ſway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is a moſt certain Truth, and there be many ancient and modern Examples of that kind; and a defaming world has ſaid, both in this and other a defaming World has ſaid, both in this and other Places, That your ſelf is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from its powerful Charms. Many, and that with too much Reaſon, will allow your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, from a betrayed <hi>Jugurtha,</hi> may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97022:16"/>to <hi>England. O! gentem venalem &amp; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doque periturarp ſi emptorem haberet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, Had the Houſe of Commons ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Point of Honour ſo far as to have believed the Dignity of their Speaker, equal to that of a <hi>Roman</hi> Proconful, and uſed the Example you have brought from a <hi>Roman</hi> Province, as a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, <hi>and thereby acquitted the Speaker, and been of the Opinion, That ſo high a Dignity was not to be ſuppoſed capable to be corrupted for having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Preſent;</hi> would you not then have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed your Praiſe with as diſplayed an Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to have fitted that Turn, as you have done this of the Speaker's being expelled? I make it no queſtion but you would have done ſo; you have your Pipe fitted to every Tune that will pleaſe the Multitude.</p>
            <p>The Action of <hi>Manlius</hi> I cannot approve, though I love ſtedfaſt Juſtice; but that is not the alone vain-glorious <hi>Roman</hi> Inſtance. It had been enough for an unfortunate Father to have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered his Son to Juſtice, and to have carried the Loſs temperately upon his Execution. There are many Examples where an ill underſtood love to ones Country has made many Nations, and in particular the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> and <hi>Carthaginians</hi> their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97022:16"/>Deſcendants, immolate to their own Children, to attone their angry Deities they worſhipped; and their Barbarity is ſo far preferable to the <hi>Romans,</hi> in that they did it in Honour tof a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Divinity, and the others for a vain Glory, and againſt Nature.</p>
            <p>Your Tranſcripts from the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> and <hi>Thucydides,</hi> I can bear: But what is your Reaſon <hi>to call</hi> Sparta <hi>a ſmall State?</hi> Do you know that it was the firſt in all <hi>Greece,</hi> and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all that famous Nation in the <hi>Perſian</hi> War? Do you know its Boundaries, Revenue, or num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Forces? Or do you call it little in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire? If the State of <hi>Sparta</hi> was little, Antiquity had nothing great.</p>
            <p>At laſt you ſoar to your higheſt Pitch. In this Place it is you believe to do Juſtice to his Majeſty's Reputation, and reflect as ſeverely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Vices of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation. But let us examin with what Capacity you do the one, and the other. <hi>It is in vain,</hi> you ſay, <hi>for the King to have raiſed the Reputation of</hi> England <hi>in War to a greater Height than it has been ſince the beginning of this Century.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though, for my own part, I think you have done the King neither Honour nor Juſtice, in confining him to the Century, (you ought in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97022:17"/>Reaſon to have carried him up to the great <hi>Henries</hi> and <hi>Edwards,</hi> nay, even to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror himſelf;) yet at the ſame time there is a Parcel of old <hi>Oliverians,</hi> and their Diſciples, about Town, who, having met with your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are ſtark mad. They ſay, That whatever Ignominy or Contempt you intend for the Race of your own Kings, you ought to remember what great Things had been done by <hi>Oliver</hi> at Sea and Land: As the Conqueſt of a great part of <hi>England,</hi> all <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland, Jamaica,</hi> and the important Town of <hi>Dunkirk.</hi> As for Sea Glory he had it, they ſay, Brim-full: For after he had beaten the <hi>Dutch</hi> he had no more any Rival upon the Water. They ſay, his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions were performed by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Force, and for not above one Million and a half <hi>per Annum</hi> at moſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is in vain that his Majeſty has acquired to us a Share in foreign Councils, which we either never had, or have utterly loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the two it muſt be: But I tell you we had formerly a Share in foreign Councils, during the greateſt of our Wars with <hi>France;</hi> we had Intereſt, in ſo far as was fit for our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, with the Emperors, Dukes of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and <hi>Britaigne;</hi> and may be it is ſometimes as
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97022:17"/>ſafe and honourable for us to manage our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils by our ſelves, as to mingle them with thoſe of deſigning Strangers; though at this Time it be moſt neceſſary during the preſent Situation of Affairs. You enlarge your Rhetorical in Vains, but I hope you will meet with a Diſappointment, when, contrary to your Aſſertion, his Majeſty ſhall find all the Satisfaction he propoſes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in heading a mighty Army upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; when he ſhall have the Glory, and we the Advantage and Satisfaction, to ſee him bring low the only Monarch in Condition to hurt him and us; and by his own Example, and Chaſtiſement of bad Men, put a Stop to Corruptions crept in among us.</p>
            <p>In the following Period you ſeem to write Vainly, for you are not to be underſtood. What do you mean <hi>by our being Maſters of a Sea to which we never pretended?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If to be Maſters in the Mediterranean be to to have a large Share of the Land on both its Banks; to have good Harbours, Authority, or Command of the Flag; there is nothing leſs. We have not one Creek or Bay, from <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars to St. <hi>Jean d'Acre,</hi> which is the whole ſtreach. We have neither <hi>Solum, Caelum;</hi> nor <hi>Portus,</hi> in all that vaſt Gulf. And if you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97022:18"/>by being Maſters, that we have got the moſt powerful Fleet in the Mediterranean, there you are Right, but your Poſition is Falſe: For <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> was in that Senſe Maſter long ago, when he ſent a Fleet againſt the <hi>African Corſairs;</hi> and to his Honour made them rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver not only all <hi>Engliſh</hi> but Chriſtian Slaves; and then <hi>England,</hi> without the help of any Confederate, was ſo. But you bring us in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Pretention there of late; have a care, Sir, what you ſay: His Catholique Majeſty, and all States who conterminate that Share, will take it ill, if we ſhould fix a Pretention to our Force; and perhaps deny us Ports, and ſend us back to the Ocean, where you ſay likewiſe we are Maſters in vain. I take this your Poſition to be in ſome Senſe true; though I could be ſatisfied you would likewiſe define what you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the Ocean: Whether it be all Seas that are not Imbayed? Or whether it be only where we have a Right to the Flag? Before the War moſt Men allowed <hi>Holland</hi> it ſelf, though inferior to <hi>England</hi> in marine Power, equal at leaſt to <hi>France,</hi> and no body but together think they are Invincible, and the greateſt Sea Force the World ever ſaw; and all happily under the command of ſo great a King. But by the way,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97022:18"/>If Force make us Maſters in the Ocean, we are undoubtedly ſo; but if together with our Force we have a Pretention to a Superiority in our own Seas, and thereby a right to the Flag, then indeed it is in vain that we are Maſters, while we are uſed like Fellow-Servants by the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Suedes;</hi> both which Nations, in the ſpace of eight Months, have braved our Flag not only in remoter Places, but in the View of our Royal Forts and Caſtles, even in the <hi>Downs:</hi> An Accident that has not happen'd within this Century, nor in the Seven laſt Reigns. But it is not to be thought that a King of ſo great Wiſdom and Courage, as is <hi>King William,</hi> can eaſiy part with a Right of which this Nation is particularly fond, and whereof it has been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorially poſſeſſed.</p>
            <p>I believe, Sir, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courage was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver called in queſtion in the time of profoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Peace, and there are many Inſtances of it by Sea and Land even then. I allow us to be happy in being under the Conduct and Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſo great a King and Captain; and I hope as it is not in vain that we are reſtored to our Laws and Liberties, ſo I truſt we ſhall never feel the Miſeries of other Nations, though we
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97022:19"/>are not exempted from ſome of our own, and thoſe even great ones.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not purſue your repeated Vanities any further; for if Vertue, Probity, and Love to our Country be wanting; and if the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Happineſs by Corruption and other inglorious Practices be ſapped, we are in a fair way to be miſerable. But I hope you will be kind to our falling Condition, and give us one Word of Comfort e're you end. His Majeſty will certainly reap Triumphal Honour for his warlike Actions and Toil; and I am ſorry that I muſt give way to your Prophetick Reproch in the Mouths of after Ages, <hi>That theſe Nations might have been happy but would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The World was once bleſt with an</hi> Epaminon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</p>
            <p>Truly, Sir, I am aſſured it is not long ſince your ſelf was bleſt with the Knowledge of that brave Greek; he might have paſſed with you for a King of <hi>Tartary</hi> ſince the Revolution. All the flouriſh of <hi>Epaminondas</hi> you bring in may ſerve as well for your next Pamphlet as for this: And why not his Cotemporary <hi>Pelopidas,</hi> who had ſome, nay a great Share, in that critical Glory of <hi>Thebes.</hi> And though you are pleaſed to ſay,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97022:19"/>That the glorious Actions of <hi>Epaminondas</hi> ſerved only to render the Fall of <hi>Thebes</hi> more conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, and leſs pitied; I am of Opinion that the <hi>Thebeans</hi> loſt their Liberty with the greateſt Honour: For their City did not out-live the Vertue of their Citizens, as did <hi>Sparta, Athens, Corinth, Argos, Maſſine;</hi> and even that Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant <hi>Rome</hi> herſelf, fell a Prey to the baſe hands of barbarous Nations, after ſhe had long out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived the great Vertue and heroick Valour of ſo many Councellors and Captains; while ſmall <hi>Thebes</hi> fell by a no leſs Perſon than the great <hi>Alexander;</hi> and in ſo Tragical a Manner, as every one may ſay, That there was more Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge than Honour in the Action, and more of <hi>Barbarian</hi> than <hi>Grecian.</hi> For the <hi>Thebeans</hi> having, after the Death of the common Enemy to <hi>Greece,</hi> and its Liberty, ſtruck off the <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian</hi> Yoke; the <hi>Athenians,</hi> upon the march of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Army, returned to their Slavery: But the magnanimous <hi>Thebeans</hi> ſtood it out; and though their Force was inferior to their Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, they did what was humanly poſſible for them in ſo great a Strait. In fine, their Force was beaten, the Citizens put to the Sword, or ſold as Slaves: And while the Aged, and ſome Women, whom the Enemies Swords had ſpared,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97022:20"/>begged the unclement Conqueror, by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the good Education beſtowed by their City upon his Father <hi>Philip,</hi> where he had been once Hoſtage in his Youth; and by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Hercules,</hi> to whom this City had given Life, and of whom the great <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf deſcended, to ſpare at leaſt their innocent Walls; the Interceſſion was in vain, ſlaughter raged every where, and <hi>Thebes</hi> was raſed.</p>
            <p>After you have gon over three Parts of the World to adorn your Pamphlet, and over all manner of Hiſtory within your Knowledge, you cannot reſt ſatisfied without a Voyage to the new World; where if you can find neither State, Kingdom, nor Philoſopher, you will have it from a Vice-roy of <hi>Mexico:</hi> You might have ſaved Charges, and have ſtaid at hom. It is an ordinary Saying, That the greateſt Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals are ſafe at the <hi>Old Baily,</hi> and every where elſe in <hi>England,</hi> provided they have Money to buy themſelves off.</p>
            <p>Next, you bring in <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Solomon. The firſt was too good for the Age he lived in, and the other foreſaw the Danger that attends a rigid Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in degenerated Times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Senſe is not eaſily underſtood; <hi>foreſee</hi> relates to the Future, and your <hi>(that attends)</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97022:20"/>to the Preſent. But I will not hit your Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical Sores, I know you do not underſtand Grammar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It were happy for a vertuous Man, according to your Opinion, to be loſt in the Croud: If he comes to be known, he runs the Hazard of being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be thought, by your excellent Advice, that ſome preaching Philoſopher is up in your Perſon; I am willing to unceil and diſabuſe the Multitude, and to tell them, That by all Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters given, you hang out a fair Colour up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as bad a Bulk as any. It is ſaid, That ſome of your own Country being unwilling you ſhould put the ſame Cheat upon us in this Place, as you have done at home, had framed the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of your obſcure Birth and Life, with all its black Articles, atteſted by Men of Probity and Honour; and that ſome good-natured <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men had intreated, or bought off, the Edge of their Anger, upon your Application to them in the Thing: But that unhappily there is ſtill an authentique preſerved, to which they pretend to add a Second Part of your Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions here in <hi>England.</hi> Where, beſides In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, Disingenuity, and want of Integrity in all your Dealing, you are ſaid to be Perjured
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97022:21"/>back and fore; that is, Sir, both ways, in a late calumnious Suit ſtirred up by you againſt ſome honeſt Gentlemen. But ſeeing there is a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility you may amend your Errors, I will not open a Shrine to ſend your infected Manners over the World, being you are a Stranger to me; and what I write is only that Mankind may be aware of your Impoſtors, and Villanies.</p>
            <p>But to come back with you to your new Friend <hi>Epicurus;</hi> that ancient Philoſopher is but your late Acquaintance neither: And to ſay the truth, you cultivate your firſt Friendſhip very honourably with him; after your having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained his Sentiment of Happineſs, you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſep to vindicate him from all Aſperſions his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation lies under from a calumnious and foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd World. I muſt tell you though, there is one of the moſt eloquent and wiſe Men of all <hi>Greece</hi> you have taken upon your Top, who has writ a particular Treatiſe againſt your ſenſible Philoſopher's Doctrine, and it were worth your while to peruſe it. After all, I perceive your Friendſhip is not without ſome Self-intereſt; you have ſcrewed from about him, though with very hard Labour, a very wandering and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond Similitude, to make up another Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97022:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>When Honour was the Reward of Vertue, it was more courted than now is Gold: and a Triumph or Statue at</hi> Rome, <hi>was infinitely more valued than all the Riches of the Eaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Sublime, Infinite and Immortal, you are pleaſed to croud every where, are Words beyond common reach; and methinks enter with as much Decency and Order in your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as ſhould do a Church-Steeple in every ordinary Dwelling-houſe. There have been Inſtances in all Ages, where there have been Men of Vertue; but I confeſs <hi>Rome</hi> has given more Examples than moſt other Cities. But it is a terrible Skip betwixt the moſt vertuous and high Time of <hi>Romes</hi> primitive Glory, and the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> betwixt your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Heroes, that affected a Triumph or Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue above all the Gold in the Eaſt, and an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure <hi>Engliſh</hi> 'Squire in 1588. If you was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to burn Incenſe to any Friend or Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, in the City or Country, deſcended of that <hi>Tilbury</hi> Heroe, you had another Time and Place for it than this. Here it is you bring ſtrange and little Gods to the Capitol without leave of the Senate: Was there never another <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man ſince the Creation, of bulk enough in Vertue to ſtand juſt next the <hi>Romans?</hi> What
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97022:22"/>do you think of many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Kings? The brave <hi>Talbots,</hi> Father and Son, whom one of our ableſt Pens do oppoſe to all Antiquity? And to whom the beſt of the <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorians now extant gives the Elogy in few Words; <hi>Talbot le plus brave de ſa Nation &amp; le plus zele pour ſa Gloire.</hi> But as to our Gentleman, who only propoſed to be Knighted; <hi>a Mark of Favour in thoſe Days granted but to a few.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would ſeem your Deſign, in this Period next, That to gratifie your Friend is to reflect upon the preſent eaſineſs to confer and obtain Honours; and yet the Merit you pretend to is no Inſtance of that, being you have not as yet obtained any. But to deal curteouſly with you, ſeeing you are pleaſed to honour my Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Loyalty and Fidelity, I will do the like for yours. They ſay, it is the Cuſtom of your Land, when your King's Hoſt (for ſo you call his Army) is in the Field, that upon the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there be many Gentlemen who bring 800 or 1000 Men into the Service, and after with great Toil and Patience they have ſerved out the Compaigne, return joyfully to their Wifes and Families, without looking for or expecting any Reward for their Fatigue and Danger, beſides that <hi>Roman</hi> one, of having done their Duty to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97022:22"/>their King and Country. And upon the matter, I think your Country-men preferable to our own, only we are better uſed to Trade than you are, and love to have ſomething for our Pains, was it never ſo little.</p>
            <p>Your Paſſion and Regret of the Inſtability of human Greatneſs in the Perſon of the great Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacon,</hi> is good and tender in you; but there were other Grounds for his ſad Fall beſides a preſent of Plate Buttons taken by one of his Servants.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Middleſex</hi> was no leſs unhappy, in being arraigned for Corruption and Bribery. Theſe be Arguments of the Severity of Fortune, and Juſtice of the Nation at a Time; with the laſt of which I confeſs I am led along to believe, That beſides the Honour that ought to reſt in the Boſom of every Peer as a Judge of the Land, an accumulated Office of the higheſt Truſt the Crown can give, is a Thing ſo tender, clean, and delicate of it ſelf, that the ſmalleſt Taſh ought to be expiated with that ſevere Chaſtiſement Bribery does deſerve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Perhaps, you ſay, I will tell you, That thoſe who gave our late Speaker the Gratuity mentioned in our Votes were to blame, and you think not.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:97022:23"/>
            <p>After which, you bring in the moſt ungen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemanly and ill Similitude in the World. Give me leave, Sir, to ſay, I know not which rides the foremoſt Horſe, your Malice or Ignorance? It is good to vindicate ones Friends, but that muſt be done by the way of Honour and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; which laſt is only known by the Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed betwixt Man and Man, and is the Light the Nation walks by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a Man of that ſordid Principle will not do you Juſtice without Money, you know not why you may not give it him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is in this Sentence both a Miſtake and Calumny. The Speaker of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons is no Judge, you can require nothing at his hand but diſpatch, and that is pinned to ſo many various Accidents, That a Preference in point of Time is an extraordinary Favour in the uncertain ſitting of a Parliament: And if a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, or ſingle Perſon, offer of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord a Gratuity, a Speaker may take or leave it, if Law does not confine him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sordid Principle</hi> is no mannerly Expreſſion. <hi>Than ſuffer by his Injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is great Ignorance: Is not the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Houſe exactly known? Is the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97022:23"/>more than a Member of 513? Has he more than one Vote? Is not there a Door every where open to your Complaint, or Petition, or Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in your Affair, until it be finiſhed?</p>
            <p>Your general Reflexion againſt ſuch as take Money is of a greater Extent than every one is aware of: You do not ſpare the Head of the Government, the King himſelf; notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his retriving you from Miſery and Starving. For what Money is given by Act of Parliament towards the War, his Majeſty cannot ſo much as apply honourably, or charitably, one Farthing otherwiſe, without your Anathema. And yet when a quite contrary Expreſſion ſuited your own Intereſt, you were as much upon the King's Part in your <hi>Obſervator N.</hi> as now you are violent againſt him in this your <hi>Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us look a little into your own Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, and find how well your Actions agree with your Precepts. You declare publickly againſt every Man's taking a Bribe, or Reward, for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving honeſt Men in Acts of Juſtice: But how does that anſwer your having taken from ſeveral Gentlemen Preſents, Bribes, and other Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Nay, rather then fail, you have taken them to the ſmall Value of 40 <hi>s.</hi> You know what in ſome meaſure chaſed you from Home,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97022:24"/>where you betrayed a young Lady contrary to the Oaths and other Obligations you lay under to her Father; which Action of it ſelf is of force to lay you under a perpetual Stigma, and brand of Infamy. Neither can I let paſs your immoral and ungentile Dealing with ſome Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, to whom you made Application, that they might lend you Threeſcore Guineas in your Neceſſity; and told them withal, That you had ſuch Intereſt with their Majeſties, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly the Queen, that you was ſure to obtain any thing at Court: It fell out that the ſame Merchants had a Ship carried into St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>'s by a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Privateer, upon pretence of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying contreband Gounds; they proffered you the Money deſired, if you ſhould obtain a Letter to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Envoy at <hi>Madrid</hi> to cauſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe the Ship; you undertook the Matter (as you uſually do with all the Impudence in the World) but having neither the Intereſt nor good Senſe to manage it, you gave them a Letter quite contrary to what their Affair required. And though it had been ſtipulated by you to return the Money in default of obtaining their Suit, you have hitherto fraudulently retained the ſame, it being not in their Power to obtain it of you by the ways of either Honour or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97022:24"/>though they would gladly give a Part to ſave the Whole: And is not this, Sir, both to rob and defraud with a Witneſs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If one, you ſay, be poſſeſſed of a Thouſand Pounds of your Money, whom neither Law nor Honour can oblige to reſtore you it, you will rather give a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Pounds than loſe all. He is a Knave to keep your Money, but you may treat him as a Robber on the High-way; give a Part to ſave the Whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a Suppoſition wherein is neither Senſe, Reaſon, good Manners, nor Similitude. The Speaker was poſſeſſed of no part of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans Money, and no Reſtitution could be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him in any manner of way. If the Argument was betwixt you, and the Squanderers of that Money, you had Reaſon to take rather one Shilling in the Pound than loſe all: Neither is their any civil Country where the Law will not reſtore you, <hi>if the Debtor be ſolvent, or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you his Perſon.</hi> If inſolvent, <hi>he is a Knave to keep your Money:</hi> Who is the Knave? This Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is very ſuitable to your Mouth and Manners, but in no caſe to the Speaker. If you chance to meet a Robber on the High-way with a Hundred Pounds about you, 'tis Ten to One
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97022:25"/>but you will think your ſelf well come of and give the Whole to ſave your Bacon.</p>
            <p>What you talk of Canon Law is impertinent: You do not underſtand the Canon Law.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Orphans Bill was the Nobleſt and Juſteſt ever came within theſe Walls; and the Managers ſaw it impoſſible to carry it on without a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thought there had been no Rule without Exceptions: What do you think of all the Bills for Settling the preſent Government in Church and State? For the Money Bills, to carry on the War for the Liberties of Mankind over almoſt all the World? But if the Nobleſt and Juſteſt, why did not the Nation interpoſe of courſe in the Orphans Favour without ſo much trouble? You ſeem of your own Head to put all the Power of the Commons in the Speaker's Perſon: If it be ſo, the Government is very unſafe, and liable to terrible Convulſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if the Managers ſaw it impoſſible to carry it on without a Gratuity, then they had Reaſon to give it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will follow, by the ſame Suppoſition, That there was an abſolute Neceſſity upon the Speaker to take it, by the Rule that Neceſſity
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97022:25"/>and Impoſſibility are inſeparable in one and the ſame Contingent.</p>
            <p>Read a little more, and you will find, That <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> having ſent to thoſe of the Iſle of <hi>Andros</hi> for Tribute, cauſed tell them, that he had ſent for that end the powerful Goddeſſes Love and Force: The <hi>Andrians,</hi> who underſtood bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Morals and Politiques than you ſeem to do, made anſwer, That they had Two as powerful to hinder them from paying, which were Neceſſity and Impoſſibility; by which you ſee how nigh theſe two lodge.</p>
            <p>The Example you bring of a Stoick Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher to aggravate the Speaker's Fault you charge him withal, is no proper Similitude. A Speaker of the Houſe of Commons has no Power in his Perſon, by the Quality of his Office, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Juſtice in his Station; that is entirely lodged in the Privilege of the Houſe, to reject or paſs a Bill. The Managers of the Orphans Bill, though they ſaw it very poſſible to obtain their Suit (whatever you are pleaſed to ſay of its being impoſſible) were willing as a Mark of their own Eſteem, and for the Pains took by Speaker in that Affair, in which the Honour of the City, as well as the Eſtates of the injured Orphans, lay at Stake, to think it their Duty to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97022:26"/>offer him a Gratuity; ſeeing there was no Law nor Practiſe upon any Record to impede them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrant, had uſurped up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Fellows in the State; had obtained to be Maſter; did Arbitrarily what he pleaſed; was a Sovereign above Law, and Juſtice: If in that caſe a Philoſopher did, againſt his Fundamental Principle of Philoſophy, humble himſelf to a Tyrant to obtain his End, he did but what is uſual at this Day in the obtaining of Suits over all Courts of the World, even where Juſtice is ſaid to Reign. But the Miſery is, the juſt Courts in our Days are more nice and inexorable than was the <hi>Sicilian</hi> Tyrant. The happy Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher was too wiſefor the unclement Tyrant; but our happy Courts are too wiſe for Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers. Come in what Shape they will, or with what Suit they pleaſe, unleſs they will or can ſpeak to the Fiſt, are ſure to be rejected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what a hopeful Condition is the Nation in when it comes to this! Where Money without Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will open the Doors, Fools and Knaves will be ſure to enter ſooner than honeſt Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have no Reaſon to complain; you are an Example and Inſtance, where neither Merit nor Money made open the Door. For your
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97022:26"/>entry into a Place that would have much better fitted an honeſt Man: And to embelliſh your Character of Gratitude, you have ſo well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed your Benefactor for the Thing, that he has been conſtrained to forbid you any more coming to his Houſe, being you detracted from and defamed that Learned Prelate where-ever you came, preferring your own Pen to his.</p>
            <p>You are pleaſed very ignorantly to bring in and miſapply a Story from the <hi>Chatlet</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt; of which I take no further Notice than to recommend you (as many have done already) to your Studies, and no more to expoſe your ſelf, ſeeing you are not now in Want and Neceſſity.</p>
            <p>Now you arrive at your laſt and Romantick Page; in this Period it is that you reſtore <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to her Glory and Splendor. You give us the Comfort, after ſo many Examples of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Vice, <hi>That the Body of the Nation is as yet incorrupted; That our Judges, Miniſters of State, and almoſt all Men in Places of Truſt, do what they can to bring Honour and Juſtice into re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt by their Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what more can we wiſh for? What more can be ſaid of the beſt Ages <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Greece</hi> in their meridian Glory ever beheld? This is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97022:27"/>not to be worſe than was <hi>Rome</hi> in the Days of <hi>Antoninus.</hi> Is not this to give the Lye to all the reſt of your Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>A Shrewsbery, <hi>a</hi> Pembroke, <hi>a</hi> Sommers, <hi>or a</hi> Holt, <hi>are not to be found in every Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You might have added, Nor in any Kingdom ſave <hi>England.</hi> You beſtow your Incenſe very ſparingly; one would think you had been Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man under <hi>Leonidas</hi> before <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Conqueſt in the Eaſt: Learn to be more ſumptuous when you entertain Men of the firſt Quality, and of ſo rare Merit. It is true, you diſtinguiſh them from the reſt of the Nation; you grant them an honourable Apartment by themſelves; you ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate them from the Croud; you grant them a favourable ſtroke of your Pen; But what is that to their Character? Your bare Expreſſion of every Age is a hackney Honour, it will ſerve every where, it will accommodate Vice as well as Vertue. If you will have ſo many <hi>Mecena's</hi> you ought to provide them a ſuitable Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Where is now your Infinite, Sublime, and Immortal? Cannot you beſtow ſome part of the Honour upon <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, of the firſt Quality and Merit, you have done upon <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Citizens and Soldiers.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:97022:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall the</hi> French <hi>King's Subjects, in ſpight of all the horid Invaſions made by that Monarch upon their Liberties, and of the innumerable Hardſhips and Miſeries his Ambition has brought upon them, continue yet to ſerve him and their Country with an inviolable Fidelity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I admired all along to find ſo little concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>French</hi> King, and his Qualities; he has been upon ſeveral Occaſions your very helpful Friend, and furniſhed you Matter for many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Sallies of Wit and Eloquence. And to ſay the truth, you have treated him very Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierly; he has neither been beholding to his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Elood with our Kings, nor to the Rank he holds in the World: They have been weak and feeble Defences, and Lines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Attaques.</p>
            <p>But I am afraid you have out-run your Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; and by your Pen in this your Period granted him to be full Maſter of the illuſtrious Crimes the noble <hi>Romans</hi> poſſeſſed, and by which inſtead of ſtooping, as you ſay, to ſo low a Quarry as Gold, they became Lords of the World. Truly, Sir, Emulation being ſet aſide, (for the which there is no great Ground in the Age we live among Princes) you have often allowed that Monarch Ambition and Thirſt after Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97022:28"/>in a ſupreme Manner, and made theſe his Qualities the original Source of the many Streams of human Blood which have run for ſo many Years almoſt over all the Fields of <hi>Europe:</hi> But you ſeem to begin to attone a little for your il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Criminal, in allowing him the Vertue and Conduct to keep the Love and Good-will of an oppreſſed and ruined People ſtill chained to his Service with an inviolable Fidelity. Is not this to exalt the <hi>French</hi> King with a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!</p>
            <p>You propoſe us the <hi>French</hi> Subjects as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Imitation, notwithſtanding all the cruel Oppreſſions put upon their Liberties by their King, and deſire us therein to <hi>imitate our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in what is Noble and Juſt;</hi> meaning, the <hi>French</hi> Submiſſion and Love to an oppreſſing King.</p>
            <p>To let paſs your ſevere Reflexion upon all <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants, I hope his Majeſty has no Reaſon, nor never ſhall have any, to doubt of the Affections of his good People; we hold our Lives, Liberties, and our All, of his Majeſty. It was his great and gallant Undertaking, his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and indefatigable Pains, his rare and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed Wiſdom, have brought us to what we ſo happily enjoy under his moſt auſpicious Reign.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:97022:28"/>
            <p>But, Sir, your Morals and Politiques ſeems to have changed their Courſe and Channel: Do you remember what you have writ for theſe Six Years by gone? Do you know upon what Foot the Nation ſtands? It is not long ſince this your <hi>French</hi> Example you propoſe would have been looked on as an Intention in you to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the Subverſion of the Government: And you are pleaſed to call it Juſt and Noble, in any oppreſſed People whoſe All is ſeized, who have nothing in Property, nay nor in Reverſion, inviolably to love and adhere to ſuch a Maſter as they have. Truly, had the two Gentlemen, who gave occaſion to your ſcandalous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, uſed ſuch Language in Print, eſtabliſhed Law could have gone far enough in puniſhing the Crime; and then it had been time for you to have levelled what Spite, Ignorance, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice could ſuggeſt againſt them: Though I dare ſay, for what is paſt, they Undervalue, Pity, and Contemn you.</p>
            <p>I dare ſay, Paſſive Obedience was never prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with more Art in the laſt Reign, than you do it in this your laſt Period: Beſides, you ruin and undermine the Foundation of the preſent Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97022:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And while our King does what's poſſible to raiſe us to (at leaſt) an equal Level with them in point of War, Let us not fall ſhort of them in thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues that make a Peace when it comes to be Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is as an unhappy a Sentence as you could have ſtumbled upon, to make the Vertues ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the Nation in time of Peace an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Fidelity, whatever Fate the poor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject may meet withal; and this you deſire we may tranſcribe from the <hi>French</hi> Copy. This was not your Advice upon <hi>England</hi> in the late Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution. Was there no other well-governed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Europe</hi> you could have propoſed for our Imitation, beſides thoſe we fight againſt, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon ſome Thouſands of miſerable Ones we daily hear of, or ſee among us, the dear Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and Country they are expelled and torn from? What do you mean, <hi>by our King's doing what is poſſible to raiſe us to (at leaſt)</hi> &amp;c. We never expected Impoſſibilities from the King; we believe his Majeſty a great Captain, and at the Head of a numerous Army; that he will do what's fit to be done in the War: Whereas you ſeem to make a previous and anteceding Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as if you foreſaw Matters would fall ſhort of our Expectation.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:97022:29"/>
            <p>
               <hi>To an equal Level.</hi> The Expreſſion is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Senſe, nor Engliſh: Beſides, it will not ſuit our Affairs, to go no farther. For what you underſtand by That, is to be in a Condition on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly never to end the War, or to be always in fear it may break out with more Violence. We muſt be in a ſuperior Sphere to our Enemies, and we have reaſon to believe it may fall out ſo. We have his Majeſties Royal Word, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides repeated Aſſurances from beyond Seas, that the Progreſs of the <hi>French</hi> Arms is ſtopt; that an End is put to that furious Career; and we are perſwaded of it by the Channel the War now runs in, by their having changed its Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, the King being Aggreſſor: And his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving broke the <hi>French</hi> Barrier where ſtrongeſt, with all the Circumſtances of Fame and Glory to himſelf, and of Shame and Diſhonour to his Enemies.</p>
            <p>But I am glad to hear the happy Word <hi>Peace</hi> begins to be heard, and appear within our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, after ſo long and cruel a War. I dare ſay, though it be in the Nature, and for the Intereſt of ſome Perſons to love that War may be continued (and your own in particular) there are many more who wiſh it at an end; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that may be ſo accompliſhed as to liberat
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97022:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>us from further Apprehenſions of what is or may be deſtructive or fatal to the true Intereſt, Religion, Liberty, and Honour of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having finiſhed to anſwer your Libel, permit me ſo far to be Nationally affected as to ſay, Wherever the Three Eſtates, or any of them, purſues violently a New Emergent as a Politique Sore, without Law, Arbitrary Power lies in that Caſe as heavy upon the Subject, as if the King invaded their Right. There is a Remedy for the Evil: It is conſentaneous and agreeable to the beſt defined human Wiſdom, That Temper intervene, until poſitive Law diſtinguiſh what ought to be done, from what ought to be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And this I take to be a Maxim inſeparable from every well-eſtabliſhed Government.</p>
            <p>I have done, and do aſſure you, That you take many more Liberties than Honour or good Senſe can allow any Man. But am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97022:30"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
